<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nature and effects of superstition in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons on Saturday the fifth of November, 1692 / by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
            <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51812</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M493</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4396</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12969092</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12969092</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96147</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51812)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96147)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 389:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nature and effects of superstition in a sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons on Saturday the fifth of November, 1692 / by Thomas Mannyngham ...</title>
                  <author>Manningham, Thomas, 1651?-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Braddyll and Robert Everingham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVII, 22 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Superstition --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96147:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NATURE and EFFECTS OF <hi>Superſtition.</hi> IN A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, ON <hi>Saturday,</hi> the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS MANNYNGHAM,</hi> D. D. and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Braddyll</hi> and <hi>Robert Everingham,</hi> and are to be Sold at the <hi>Seven Stars</hi> in <hi>Ave-Mary-Lane,</hi> MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:96147:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96147:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts XVII. 22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then <hi>Paul</hi> ſtood in the midſt of Marſ-Hill and ſaid, ye Men of Athens, I percieve that in all things ye are too Superſtitious.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS is the beginning of that moſt wiſe and excellent Speech, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> made in the great Court of <hi>Athens,</hi> where many of the Philoſophers and Learned Men of <hi>Greece</hi> where Aſſembled to gratifie their Curioſity, and to hear what that <hi>New Doctrine</hi> was, which he ſeemed ſo deſirous of Publiſhing amongſt them. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> talk'd ſo much of <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96147:3"/>took him to be a ſetter-forth of New Gods, and one who came to increaſe the Superſtition of the Vulgar; for we cannot well conceive that all the Philoſophers of that Age, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Epicureans,</hi> which was the moſt prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sect at that Time, had any great Opinion of thoſe Devotions and Ways of Worſhip, of which the Common People were ſo Zealous: However, they expected ſomething that was new, ſomething that might entertain their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive Minds, and give ſome Diverſion to their Wit and Parts.</p>
            <p>The Religion of the great Men of that Age was wholly turn'd into curious Diſputes, into elegant Diſcourſes, and a Gentile Way of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and anſwering ſome <hi>ſpecious Probabilities,</hi> and of making their Converſations very eaſie as to matter of Opinions. They were ſufficiently conſcious that ſome of the Idolatries of the World were too <hi>Groſs</hi> and <hi>Abſurd</hi> to bear the name of Religion, and too <hi>Inhuman</hi> to be practiſed by a civiliz'd People. Some <hi>Popular</hi> Worſhips they found it neceſſary to allow of, ſuch as might give Amuſement, and not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the Commonwealth: They had ſubtile Diſtinctions and Evaſions for themſelves, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96147:3"/>ſo the Multitude would be but quiet and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable, and not diſturb their ſoft Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; They were content that many fanciful Rites and Dotages ſhould prevail, and be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by their Laws.</p>
            <p>It is eaſie to read this <hi>Epicurean</hi> Temper in the Behaviour of moſt of thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, who were concerned in the Affairs of <hi>Judea;</hi> and their own Hiſtories acquaint us that this was the Temper which then gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally prevailed among their Great Men: Their main Buſineſs was Empire and Eaſe, they did not care to trouble themſelves much about the Queſtions and Zeal of contending Parties, but ſuffered all Men to enjoy their particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, ſo they raiſed no Tumults, and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nothing contrary to the Intereſt of <hi>Caeſar.</hi> This was the Humour of the <hi>Epicurean</hi> Party, though others were of ſomewhat a warmer Temper.</p>
            <p>Now St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was not afraid of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> his Draught, ſpake ſuch Truths before the Magiſtrates, and the moſt captious Sects, and in that City too, which was the Metropolis of all Idolatry, with that Freedom and Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as few of their wiſe Men, had they been able, would have ventured to have ſo publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96147:4"/>own'd; who, though they were conſcious of ſome Truth, yet for the moſt part detain'd it in Unrighteouſneſs: But our Apoſtle, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted manner, declares unto them, the God of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the God, who made the World and All Things, the God, whom they themſelves did ignorantly Worſhip; to whom they had erected an Altar, though they had appointed no Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>There were ſome few of the more Thinking Men, both among the <hi>Athenians</hi> and the <hi>Romans,</hi> who had gone a great way in diſcovering and confuting the Follies and Barbarities of the more monſtrous Sorts of Superſtition; they could, in a great meaſure, pull down the old Buildings, but knew not how to erect a new one; they were vigorous Oppoſers of ſome very palpable Falſhoods, but knew not where to find the Truth: Whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> not only diſcovered the egregious Vanity of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> but ſet before them the true and only Religion; the Worſhip of one God, <hi>v.</hi> 23. ſincere Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>v.</hi> 30. ſtedfaſt Belief of a Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an expreſs and peculiar Faith in that Man whom God had ordain'd to Judge the whole World in Righteouſneſs, of which he had given a full aſſurance and demonſtration,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96147:4"/>by raiſing him from the Dead, <hi>verſe</hi> 31.</p>
            <p>Now, if we throughly conſider St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments againſt the Superſtitions of the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> we ſhall find that they have a Foundation in <hi>natural Religion,</hi> but their main ſtrength and laſt Evidence is built upon <hi>Revelation:</hi> For he reaſons with them, That there is one God the Maker of Heaven and Earth, and all things therein; that nothing is more abſured than to make any material Repreſentation of the Infinite Being: That Man is but an Off-ſpring of God, and if no Art can repreſent Man's Reaſon and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by any Image in Gold, Silver or Stone, how much leſs can it figure out the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Godhead, of which Man's Soul is but an imperfect Image? That God is not to be worſhipped with any Opinion of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digency in him, as if he needed any thing, as they ſuppoſed their <hi>Daemons</hi> did, who, as they fancied, were pleas'd, and, as it were, fed with the Steams of their Sacrifices; whereas he, who was Lord of Heaven and Earth, wanted nothing, and would be Worſhipped for our Advantage, not his own: That he was the Creator of all Mankind, having made of one Blood all Nations of Men. That his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence was over all, in Suſtaining and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96147:5"/>all Things: That though he had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the ignorant World to try their own ways, yet now he commanded all Men to Repent: And to confirm the general appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion they had of a Day of Judgment, and to make it a certain Principle of all their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Actions, he appeals to <hi>Revelation;</hi> tells them of an Appointed Day, and of the very <hi>Perſon</hi> whom God had Ordain'd to Judge the World in Righteouſneſs; and leaſt they ſhould think that he intended to remove one Superſtition, only, to bring in another, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to ſuch a Teſtimony, to ſuch a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Confirmation, as God would never give to any thing but Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> to a Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Dead: The Truth of which, if he himſelf had not been ready to have Seal'd with his own Blood, he would never have ventur'd to Preach <hi>Jeſus</hi> and the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Athens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, having enlarged upon this Excellent and moſt weighty Speech, wherein St. <hi>Paul,</hi> with admirable Addreſs, reproved the <hi>Athenians</hi> for their Superſtition, and took an occaſion to inſinuate his own Doctrine with leſs Offence (for if they were ſo Hoſpitable to all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, why ſhould they be backward in giving
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96147:5"/>Entertainment to his) and wherein he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes the main Body of Heatheniſm by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon, of which they pretended to be the greateſt Maſters, and by the Authority of <hi>Aratus,</hi> an Aſtronomical Poet of high Repute amongſt them; and laſtly, wherein he not only confutes their Errors, but ſhews them the Truth; not by ſubtilty and human Methods, but by having recourſe to the Revelation of God, and that teſtify'd, by the greateſt of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the Dead; having thus enlarg'd upon this Oration of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which he made againſt the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> in the midſt of their great Court of Judicature, I ſhall endeavour theſe three Things in my following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. To lay down ſome Conſiderations that may lead us into a more diſtinct Knowledg of the Nature of Superſtition.</item>
               <item>II. To obſerve ſome of its more Barbarous Effects, ſuch as the Occaſion and the Hiſtory of this Day ſhall ſuggeſt.</item>
               <item>III. To propoſe ſome Directions to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from this Horrible Sin, and the ill Conſequences of it.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96147:6"/>
            <p n="1">I. To lay down ſome Conſiderations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Superſtition in its ordinary uſe, is made a word of Ambiguity, and a common Term of Diſdain, which is mutually caſt upon all the Differences in Religion. The <hi>Epicureans</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it Superſtition to acknowledge the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, and to pay him any Worſhip beſides the bare Eſteem of the Mind. The Heathen Writers, whenever they mention the <hi>Jews</hi> or the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſpeak of them as a moſt wretchedly-deluded People, given over to an obſtinate Superſtition: But I think the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fathers have ſufficiently manifeſted where Superſtition was to be really charg'd, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their Abſurd, Cruel and Obſcene Rites, and by Baffling all the Arguments which they brought to juſtifie their Follies.</p>
            <p>But ſtill, there are vaſt Bodies of People in the World, who live under different Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in Religion, as well as under different Governments; who are mightily ſatisfied in their own ways of Worſhip, and commiſerate all who are not of their Opinion, as poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Creatures blinded with Superſtition. Nay, the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity it ſelf, is ſo fill'd up with different Imaginations, Rites and Uſages, that almoſt all diſtinct Communions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96147:6"/>are Impeaching and Abhorring one another, upon the account of Superſtition.</p>
            <p>They who know the World, know that theſe are true Obſervations, and very deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: But ſure there is ſome better Standard of Superſtition than the opprobrious Language and Paſſions of Mankind, and that is the thing I am now to enquire after.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Therefore, 'tis well known, that <hi>Plutarch</hi> has written the moſt celebrated Treatiſe on this Subject, of any among the Ancient Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; for that Book of <hi>Seneca</hi> concerning Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> quotes, is not come down to our Hands. Now, though this Grave and Ingenious Author has deliver'd many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Things on that Head, and ſhew'd an extraordinary Zeal againſt thoſe who painted the Divinity in a Horrid Shape, that they might Worſhip their own <hi>ill Nature;</hi> yet when he defines Superſtition by an <hi>Aſtoniſhing</hi> and <hi>Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Apprehenſion</hi> of the <hi>Deity,</hi> he does not tell us the true <hi>Nature</hi> of it, but only points out one <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or one <hi>Occaſion</hi> of it: For though Superſtition may ariſe from Fear, yet it riſes alſo from Ignorance, or a Stupidity of the Mind, from Love and Fondneſs, as well as from Fear, from almoſt any Paſſion of the Soul, and any Temper of the Body; for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96147:7"/>when the Natural Sence of a Deity, and of the Duty that Man owes him, comes to be vitiated with a mixture of Mens own Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Paſſions, thoſe Infirmities and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſtand ready to commence Superſtition; there being nothing more requir'd, but an Opinion of their being <hi>well-pleaſing to God,</hi> which is ſeldom wanting to Mens own Imaginations. Beſides, to call a Dread of God by the Name of Superſtition, is ſomewhat a dangerous Expreſſion to Chriſtian Ears, when we conſider how the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> does almoſt every where repreſent Religion by the Fear of God; and that the Prophets convers'd with him under great Tremblings and Terror. <hi>Plutarch</hi> was a <hi>Platoniſt,</hi> and the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> were a Sect of People who were generally of a ſoft and Amorous Nature, who plac'd their Happineſs in the Speculation of Ideas; and who rarely conſider'd God, as a Righteous Puniſher of Sin, but chiefly as a moſt amiable Being for them to contemplate; they uſually entertain'd very good Opinions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and of their own Perfections, and little thought of that Gulf which Sin had made between Man and the Divine Nature; and therefore they hardly allow'd ſuch a juſt Severity to the Deity, as was requiſite for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96147:7"/>wiſe Government of the World, but made his Goodneſs to ſwallow up his Juſtice. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God, who knows his own Nature beſt, has given us another Character of himſelf, <hi>the Lord, Merciful and Gracious, and forgiving Iniquity; but will by no means clear the Guilty, viſiting the Iniquities of the Fathers upon the Children,</hi> Exod. 34.6, 7. Superſtition therefore, though varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in its Original and Effects, is always found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon a falſe Apprehenſion of God, and conſequently upon a falſe Apprehenſion of Religion, by which he is Serv'd and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip'd: And as this falſe Apprehenſion of God and Religion ariſes from ſeveral Cauſes, and produces ſeveral Effects, ſo accordingly Superſtition is varied; It conſiſts both in Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Practice; and though Practice be moſt Obvious and Remarkable, and that from which Opinion is uſually gather'd; yet it may be defin'd, with a regard to both, <hi>viz. That it is the Performing of a religious Service, with an Opinion of its being well-pleaſing to God, though it be really unacceptable and unworthy to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to him.</hi> So that our next Enquiry will be, to know what Religious Service is well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God, and what is unacceptable to him.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Some have thought that the Manners and Cuſtoms of the Country, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96147:8"/>Laws are the only Determination in this Matter: So <hi>Seneca</hi> is repreſented by St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> for concluding that thoſe Superſtitions which he could not approve of to his own Mind, were yet to be obſerv'd, becauſe the Laws commanded them: <hi>Quae omnia ſapiens obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, tanquam legibus juſſa, non tanquam Diis grata,</hi> C. D. l. 6. c. 10.</p>
            <p>And not much unlike is, that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Aſſigns, when ſhe makes her Conſtitutions the only meaſure of what is, and what is not, Superſtition.</p>
            <p>But now this is a way of confounding all Truth, or of making it ſafe, as to Temporal Intereſt, for Men to practice the Superſtitions of every Country, where they are publickly allowed; but this gives the Mind no Light, nor enables it to make a Rational and Certain Diſtinction between Religion and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An Appeal to the Principles of Natural Religion, and to the Dictates of ſound Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, did go a great way among ſome of the wiſer Heathen towards the Determination of this Thing; and therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> inſiſted ſo much upon Natural Principles in his Speech to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> though he did not ultimately reſt on thoſe: Groſs Idolatry could not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96147:8"/>the Light of Natural Reaſon, when it was well diſplay'd; but yet there were many leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Extravagances from which the politer Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then could not free themſelves by the ſtrength of that Principle. Thus <hi>Cicero,</hi> who was a great Maſter of Morality, and deeply ingag'd in all the Gallantry of Roman Vertue and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Worth, made a ſhift, by the Sagacity of his Reaſon, and the Natural Probity of his Mind, to confute the more Abominable Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Practices of the Superſtitious in his Time; whatſoever was Barbarous and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whatſoever was Obſcene and Filthy, and Egregiouſly abſurd in the Gentile Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, he perfectly deteſted, as directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Benignity of God, to the Modeſty of Human Nature, to the Univerſal Love of Mankind, and the Foundation of all Society: But when he had work'd his Reaſon to ſome height, and had proceeded ſo far as to give a good blow to all Paganiſm, by his Rational and Searching Diſcourſes; yet, at laſt, he found it neceſſary to retain ſome Sacrifices, and ſome Ceremonies in the Worſhip of the Gods; for which he could give no other reaſon than the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Oracles,</hi> and the <hi>Tradition</hi> of <hi>Anceſters.</hi> And this plainly ſhews, that there is no reſting in this Argument, till we come to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96147:9"/>
               <hi>Divine Revelation.</hi> We may, doubtleſs, go a great way towards the detecting of Superſtition by the ſtrength of that which Men call Natural Religion and Moral Principles, and the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Reaſon of Things; for whatſoever is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently repugnant to the Notion of the Godhead, to the Perfection of our own Nature, and to the beſt Conceptions of our Minds, can never be the whole, or any part of the true Worſhip of God: But though this be freely granted, yet I ſuppoſe that Man would be hard put to it, that ſhould undertake to prove that the Ceremonial Worſhip of the Ancient <hi>Jews</hi> was not Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be allow'd no Arguments to prove this by, but ſuch as ariſe from the natural No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Things, and a ſuitableneſs to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature: Had not God been pleaſed to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute that Worſhip Himſelf, and to give Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to it, by a multitude of undeniable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, we ſhould never have found any intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal Goodneſs in it, by hearkning to our own Reaſon, or by contemplating the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So likewiſe, in reſpect to the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chriſtian Religion, what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity can we diſcover between thoſe material and ſenſible Ceremonies, and a pure and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Spirit? 'Tis true, they are admirably ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Worſhip of a <hi>God Incarnate,</hi> but then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96147:9"/>that is matter of Revelation, and is the thing I contend for; <hi>viz.</hi> That we can never boldly pronounce concerning what is true Religion, and what is Superſtition, till we fix our ſelves upon <hi>Divine Revelation:</hi> For though, as I have obſerv'd, ſome of the wiſer among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> were able, by Natural Reaſon, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover ſome of the groſſer Parts of Superſtition, yet ſtill they themſelves were under the ſame Bondage, though in a leſs Degree; as ſome Madmen, who are leſs Raving, will oftentimes ſpeak with ſome Judgment and Compaſſion of the more Extravagant Madneſs of others, tho' all the while they too labour under the ſame Diſeaſe, but their Diſeaſe is not in ſo high a Ferment.</p>
            <p>We muſt centre our ſelves therefore upon the Reveal'd Will of God in Matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and not truſt too much to our own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings concerning the Divine Nature and Will, of which we ſhould have known ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but very little, if God had not been pleaſed to diſcover himſelf to us in his holy O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: If Men ſhall go to make Religion, or any part of it out of their own Heads, they will certainly make a Superſtition of it: There is not ſo much as a purely <hi>Natural</hi> Religion in the fall'n State of Mankind; no Prayers or Praiſes,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96147:10"/>or any of thoſe we call Natural Duties, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God without an Expiation, and an Interceſſor; and theſe Things depending on the Will of God, can be no otherwiſe known, than as he has revealed them. Wherefore true Religion is keeping cloſe to the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of God in all the Eſſentials, and in all the ſubſtantial Acts of Worſhip, and Superſtition is a departing from it in any of theſe. All the uſe we have of Reaſon in the Buſineſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is to lead us to Divine Relation, and then to aſſiſt us in finding out the true Sence and Meaning of what is there deliver'd; and when this is done, we are wholly to reſign our ſelves to the Will of God, and to believe and do as he has Commanded.</p>
            <p>To effect this, Reaſon may proceed in this Method, and by theſe Fundamental Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xims.</p>
            <p>That God may reveal his Will to Mankind in a Supernatural and Extraordinary Manner: That he can make uſe of ſufficient means to confirm his Revelations to us, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to diſtinguiſh between a true Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and a pretended one: That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God Reveals is infallibly true: That if we will make a ſincere Uſe of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties we may ſo far underſtand the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96147:10"/>true Senſe of whatever God has reveal'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to his Worſhip, as to diſtinguiſh his Mind from falſe Interpretations, and to be ſecure, that we have right Objects for our Faith, and true Rules and Meaſures for our Obedience: But then farther, 'tis as Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional a Concluſion, as any of the foregoing, that God can reveal more than we can fully comprehend; or, that he can diſcover to us ſuch ſublime Truths, as we may have ſufficient Reaſon to believe, tho' we have not Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties fully to conceive; and it is here eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our Reaſon is to ſtoop, and to yield to Faith; for our Underſtandings are finite, and not a proper Meaſure of all Divine Truth; and what is more to be inſiſted on, they have contracted many <hi>Weakneſſes,</hi> and much, Blindneſs in <hi>Spiritual</hi> things; and upon theſe Accounts, it becomes us to be exceeding cautious, leſt we ſhould take our Baffions and our Prejudices, for plain and evident Reaſon.</p>
            <p>By theſe ſteps, together with the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Tradition of thoſe Miracles and Matters of Fact, which are Recorded in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, a Man may arrive to a <hi>Rational Faith;</hi> and then he may ſecurely pronounce, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96147:11"/>there is but one <hi>True Religion,</hi> or acceptable Worſhip, which is the <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and that all the reſt are Superſtitious, whether <hi>Jewiſh, Pagan,</hi> or <hi>Mahometan;</hi> for the <hi>Jewiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as 'tis now profeſs'd in oppoſition to Chriſt, and as 'tis ſtuff'd with modern Dotages, is a poor, wretched Superſtition.</p>
            <p>As to what concerns the charge of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition among Chriſtians, it may now be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd in few words: For I do not ſee, that it can with any manner of Truth, be apply'd to any viſible Public <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> but that of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for I do not concern my ſelf at preſent, with the multitude of unformed Sects. It cannot conſiſt, either in the numerouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or oddneſs of Ceremonies, when there is no Merit attributed to them, and they are not enjoin'd as Subſtantial Acts of Worſhip, or as parts of Holineſs, in themſelves well pleaſing to God.</p>
            <p>As to Superſtition in Manners, or the bad uſe which ſome make of the Externals of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that cannot be prevented by the moſt excellent Conſtitution of a Church, nor by the beſt Wiſdom of a Nation; for when People are averſe to real Goodneſs, they will try to go to Heaven by ſhifts, and place Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Inſtrumental Piety; Theſe are abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96147:11"/>which cannot be wholy prevented by any Public Eſtabliſhment; but People muſt be call'd off from ſuch ſort of Superſtition, by frequent Admonitions, and by ſuch Sermons and Diſcourſes, as ſhall plainly ſhew, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in real and ſubſtantial Holineſs does conſiſt. Whereas the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> has Eſtabliſh'd Superſtition by a <hi>Law,</hi> and made it the moſt Celebrated part of their Worſhip and Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A great part of their Religion is founded upon ſome particulars, which they conjecture, muſt needs be Tranſacted by Souls departed, and in the behalf of Souls, as they are in a State of <hi>Separation,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which Revelation has left us in the dark; wherefore, that muſt neceſſarily be a very great Superſtition, which obliges People to receive ſuch practices, as parts of Divine Worſhip, which have nothing to ſupport them, but Man's Preſumption. The Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Saints and Angels, is Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the principal Senſe of the Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Worſhip of Demons; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the fine colours, by which their witty Men try to diſguiſe this practice; 'tis hard to propoſe any two things in the world, that run in ſo exact a parallel, as the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96147:12"/>Worſhip of <hi>Demons</hi> among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Worſhip of <hi>Saints</hi> among the Papiſts; a Parallel, not forc'd and ſought for, nor mannag'd by fanſie, but ſuch as obtrudes it ſelf upon the Obſervation, and offers it ſelf to our firſt Reflections. Little did St. <hi>Paul</hi> think, when he made his admirable Speech againſt the Superſtition of the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that he himſelf ſhould one day be Worſhip'd as a ſort of <hi>Demon</hi> in the Chriſtian Church: But ſo it is, the Seducer has been too hard for thoſe Chriſtians, who would not ſtand to the plain Word of God, but would preſume to make Additions to the main and principal part of all Revelation, the Doctrine of the Mediation of Chriſt: He has inſinuated a moſt abominable Idolatry, which is the worſt part of Superſtition, under another dreſs; he has ſupply'd the Papiſts, with Angels and Saints, inſtead of Demons and Hero's, and has ſent them <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having laid down ſome Conſiderations, that may lead us into a more diſtinct Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Nature of Superſtition; I proceed in the</p>
            <p>Second place, to obſerve ſome of its more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96147:12"/>barbarous Effects, ſuch as the preſent Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Hiſtory of this Day ſhall ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt.</p>
            <p>Had we only the <hi>Follies</hi> and <hi>Impieties</hi> of Superſtition to complain of, it were a Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance worthy the Care and Wiſdom of a Chriſtian Nation to provide againſt; but when we conſider, that nothing animates Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more to <hi>Sedition,</hi> and to an abhorrence of all good Government, than Superſtition; that it is the moſt fruitful parent of ignorant and bitter Zeal; that the moſt cruel Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, and moſt miſchievous Deſigns are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſuggeſted by Superſtitious Councils, and moſt commonly attempted by Men of Enthuſiaſtick Tempers, embolden'd by falſe Opinions in Religion; when we conſider theſe things, and what a peculiar Malignity there is in all Superſtition againſt the Civil Peace of Kingdoms, and the ſafety of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick States; there ſeems to lye a <hi>new Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> to hinder the increaſe of that Diſtemper in Religion, which is ſo apt to turn into the <hi>worſt Plague</hi> of Government, a <hi>Rebellion upon pretence of Conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſ. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> obſerves of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> of his time, that they would hardly obey any Magiſtrates, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96147:13"/>hearken to any Laws, upon the account of their numerous Superſtitions. And the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of our own Times may ſatisfie any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Perſon, that when ever People of ſuch Perſwaſions and Tempers ſhall be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to come to a Head, there will ſoon be an end of all juſt Authority: For what legal Reſtraint can be laid upon thoſe, who preſume themſelves actuated in all things by a Divine Impulſe, and that all the Murders they commit, are but ſo many Acceptable Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to God? and who will be ſure to throw off their Civil Subjection, as ſoon as ever it ſhall come into their Fancies, that God will help them againſt their Magiſtrates?</p>
            <p>The Conſpiracy of this day is Evidence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, what Cruel and Barbarous Deſigns Superſtition is always big with, tho', God be thank'd, it has not always ſtrength to bring forth: Nothing, it ſeems, could content thoſe Superſtitious Zealots, but the choiceſt Sacrifice, made up of the nobleſt Blood, and the Flower of Humane Nature gather'd into one body: And that there might be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to oppoſe their helliſh Deſign, they were reſolv'd not to give the blow, till all the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Wiſdom, and Courage of the Nation
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96147:13"/>were met in one Auguſt Aſſembly; but Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, which preſides over Kingdoms, is eſpecially watchful over Parliaments, by which Kingdoms are beſt ſecur'd; and ſtill continues a Succeſſion of Them to withſtand all Popiſh Counſels and Attempts, and to praiſe the Lord for that great Deliverance.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing many are not apt to be ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſibly affected with thoſe Deliverances, which were conferr'd on the Generations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; behold! this Day has been ſince enlarged with <hi>new Mercies,</hi> and therefore requires a double Gratitude from us. When the Men of the ſame Superſtition had brought another horrible Deſign almoſt to effect, of undermining the Government, and of blowing up the Laws and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this Kingdom and Church; even that was as miraculouſly prevented by a Divine and ſeaſonable Interpoſal; and it muſt needs raiſe our Wonder and Joy, when we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who that Deliverer was, that Providence ſent us: A Royal Prince out of that very Line, which was on this Day devoted to an utter Extinction: A Prince born ſo near this almoſt fatal Day, his Birth having an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate priority to this Anniverſary, that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96147:14"/>thereby ſeems to aſſure us, that He has an Aſcendant over all the Malignant Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Popiſh Sorcery; and that their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ſhall never prevail againſt him; and that by his very Nativity, he is pointed out to be the Guardian of the Proteſtant Cauſe: And what is another remarkable Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in our Deliverer, he is a Prince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from that Noble Anceſtor of his, who withſtood the Tyranny and growing Monarchy of <hi>Spain,</hi> when ſhe thought to have graſp'd all the Liberties of <hi>Europe;</hi> and having drank deep of the Cup of Fornications, had given her Power and her Strength unto the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe are Conſiderations that would tempt any Rational Man, tho' of no Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Genius, to conclude, that doubtleſs, ſome greater Revolution than what we have yet experimented, is moving on; unleſs our Ingratitude ſtop it.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the Mercies that we have every Year Commemorated ſince that happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution, we are ſtill to bleſs God, that we have our Eſtabliſh'd Religion, and may ſerve him without a Slaviſh and Superſtitious Fear. That our King is ſtill Vigorous and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96147:14"/>Active, to watch and to withſtand, a very Subtil, Powerful, and Implacable Enemy. Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle do People think, what an inſtance it is of God's eſpecial Goodneſs towards us, that we are nor given over as a Prey unto his Teeth, that He can only Attempt and Threaten, and that His terrible fierceneſs is ſtill bound up and reſtrain'd, tho' not confounded; That we have ſtruck a hook into the Jaw of that Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan, by our late Victory at Sea, and hope, in a ſhort time, to take an effectual care, that that <hi>Leviathan</hi> ſhall no longer take his Paſtime in the deep. And tho' it be an <hi>Amphibious</hi> Creature that we have to deal with, whoſe greateſt Strength lyes on the Land; yet by a prodigious Gallantry, of ſome of the Braveſt Men that ever gave their Lives for their Country; He has been lately taught, that it would not be ſo hard for us to Conquer, if he had but Courage to give us one fair Battel.</p>
            <p>'Tis not the Method of Divine Providence, to do all for us at once, but to try our Gratitude, by ſeveral inſtances of his goodneſs gradually diſpens'd, and to mingle ſome Hardſhips with the Deliverances he ſends us; to ſee whether we will repent and amend, and whether we are worthy of the continuance of his Favour.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96147:15"/>If he finds by the daily increaſe of Wickedneſs amongſt us, that he ſhall not be Glorify'd by our Proſperity, he will change his Method of dealing with us, and be Glorify'd in our Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. If we grow ſo nice, as to murmur at his proceedings, becauſe they do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly anſwer to all our Deſires; if we prove ſo unreaſonable, as to think we are undone, becauſe our Safety puts us to ſome Expences; and if our Condition appear miſerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Bleſſings are ſomewhat chargeable to us; then have we Reaſon to fear, leſt our Repining ſhould provoke God to make us Drink deeper of the Cup of Afflictions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gives us a farther Delivery.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of the Goſpel have been often put to make Apologies for the darker Providences of God; but the untoward Temper of this Age puts us upon making A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologies for his very Mercies too: Men have been ſo much us'd to Infidelity, that they will not believe their own Temporal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if they can find the leaſt thing to object againſt it.</p>
            <p>We all underſtand what Diſcontents there are in this Kingdom; (and can any of you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, when this Nation was without its
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96147:15"/>Complaints?) we know what ill Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſome are ready to make of every Management, and of every Event; we grant there are many difficulties under which we lye at preſent, and that the carrying on of ſo Neceſſary and ſo Diffuſive a War, muſt needs be our burthen, as well as our Security; but none of theſe things muſt put a damp upon our Spirits, leſſen our Gratitude to God, or check our forwardneſs in contributing large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards the Maintaining of that Cauſe, in which the whole Proteſtant Intereſt is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd; and in which his Majeſty has been ſo Nobly ſeconded, by the concurrent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, of a Wiſe, a Senſible, and a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Parliament.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I come in the laſt place, to lay down ſome Directions, to preſerve us from the Horrible Sin of Superſtition, which is one great occaſion of all the Troubles of this Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And here I beg leave, to recommend Three Things more eſpecially.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The firſt is, a thorough inſight into the Law of Nature, and the obligation of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Actions; an excellent piece of Wiſdom, and brought to great Perfection in ſome late
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96147:16"/>Writings: The ſtudy of this, will render Mens Judgments ſound and maſculine, make them leſs lyable to Superſtitious Fancies, and conſequently leſs ſubject to Atheiſtical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, which many run into, by an Injudicious and too haſty abhorrence of the other. Make but a ſober Enquiry into the True Nature of Humane Actions, and that will quickly Teach you, to diſtinguiſh between Moral Duties, and Ritual Performances, and Barbarous Impieties, acted under the pretence of Religion; and to prefer Obedience, Righteouſneſs, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Mercy, before the Sacrifice of Fools and Madmen; it will bring you to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that your beſt Actions fall below your Rule, and then the Defects of Morality, will directly lead you to ſeek after an Expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for thoſe Defects, and that Expiation is Chriſt our Saviour.</item>
               <item>2. Do but take a ſerious view of the horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Superſtitions of the Ancient and Modern Heathen, and you will quickly abhor all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches towards ſuch Degeneracies from common Reaſon, and from the firſt Notions of Religion; and not indure that Chriſtianity ſhould have any of thoſe ſordid mixtures brought into it; which in time would make
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96147:16"/>that Heavenly Inſtitution an Inſtrument of the vileſt practices in the World: For when once the Superſtitious get a Head, there will be no ſtopping of them; they will rage in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bloody and barbarous Effects; in the deſtruction of Cities, Families, Provinces, as very acceptable parts of Devotion; they will proceed, for all that I know, from Plots and Maſſacres, to worſhip God directly by Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Sacrifices; from the attempting to blow up Parliaments, to the offering up their own Sons and Daughters unto Devils.</item>
               <item>3. Do but peruſe the Hiſtory of the Church in its firſt and pureſt Ages, and you will wonder how that Grave Matron, the Chriſtian Religion, came to put on ſuch a meretricious Paint, as it appears with in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> how old plainneſs and Sincerity came to be ſo ſupplanted by Artifice and Fraud; how Goodneſs, Candor, Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, and lawful Subjection came to be run down by Fury and Rebellion, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Conſpiracies undertaken with Ceremonies of Religion; and how the moſt Solemn Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of one God, thro' one Mediator, came to be turn'd almoſt into the Worſhip of one Pope, and all ſuch Saints as he ſhall pleaſe to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96147:17"/>Canonize; either for their Holineſs, or for their Villany.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. For a general Direction to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who would not be enſnar'd by Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I intreat them to ſtand to the Holy Scriptures, and to well ſeaſon their Minds with a due ſenſe of the Chriſtian Religion from thoſe Pure and Spiritual Diſcourſes which our Saviour himſelf has left us: To conſider, what are the eſpecial Duties to which he has annexed his Bleſſings, and what is the Hypocriſie and Formal Worſhip he has moſt zealouſly oppos'd. 'Tis converſing much with the Holy Scriptures, that alone is able to make a Man Devout and Diſcreet at the ſame time; there is no ſuch ſecurity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Superſtition, as a conſtant recourſe to the Word of God, that Cryſtal Fountain of all Truth, Holineſs, Wiſdom, and Love; and when theſe Graces are well infus'd into our Hearts, nothing but what is ſolid in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion will be able to make any ſtrong Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on our Souls.</p>
            <p>To conclude, That which I am willing to leave very affecting and warm upon your Minds, is this, That I fear our little Differences in Politicks, have very much abated of that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96147:17"/>juſt abhorrence which is due to the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Superſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and ſo the laſt Error may be worſe than the firſt: But whatever miſcarriages we mutually impute to each other, let us all aſſure our ſelves, that <hi>Popery</hi> is ſtill the ſame Corruption of Chriſtianity as before, and that there is no Alteration in the Opinions and Deſigns of that Church, whatever there may be in the Piety and Conſtancy of thoſe who ſeem to ſlacken very much in their Oppoſition againſt it. Let us endeavovr to behave our ſelves with that Moderation, that all Parties may come into the true Intereſt of the Nation, which is the preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion; that all our Hearts may be united into the ſame general Policy and Wiſdom; that our Diviſions may be no longer a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to our ſelves, and a Triumph to our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And, in a word, that Luxurious <hi>Faſts,</hi> Murmuring <hi>Thanksgivings,</hi> and falſe Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Allegiance</hi> may not be the ruin of this Church and Kingdom! If neither Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments nor Mercies will do us any good; if we are of too perverſe a Temper, either to be Humbled or Oblig'd, then our greateſt Calamity is not remov'd, but only deferr'd;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96147:18"/>but if we have Hearts truly thankful for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Deliverances, and have the Grace and Skill to manage a preſent Bleſſing, when 'tis put into our Hands, we may ſtill be a Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and a Great People, and ſuch as the Lord ſhall delight to viſit with Mercies, Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, and a mighty Salvation: <hi>Which God of his Infinite Mercy grant us; thro' Jeſus Chriſt, his Son, our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, Glory, Power, Praiſe and Thanksgiving, now and for ever more.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96147:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
